<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The defence of a certayne poore Christen man who els shuldhaue [sic] bene condemned by the Popes lawe. Written in the hye Allmaynes tonge by a right excellent and noble prynce, and tra[n]slated into Englishe by Myles Couerdale.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5889</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849759</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177901</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12249)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177901)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1268:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The defence of a certayne poore Christen man who els shuldhaue [sic] bene condemned by the Popes lawe. Written in the hye Allmaynes tonge by a right excellent and noble prynce, and tra[n]slated into Englishe by Myles Couerdale.</title>
                  <author>Coverdale, Miles, 1488-1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S. Mierdman] And translated owt of douche in to Englishe by Myles Couerdale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at Nurembergh [i.e. Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yeare of our Lorde. M.D.XLV. in the laste of Octobre. [1545]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Folger Shakespeare Library Catalogue suggests Richard Pygge as printer.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Marsh's Library, Dublin.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The defence of a certayne poore Chriſten man: Who els ſhuld haue bene condemned by the Popes lawe.</p>
            <p>¶ Written in the hye Allmaynes tonge by a right excellent and noble Prynce / and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated into Engliſhe by Myles Couerdale.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>oue conſtrayneth me me (Right vertuous Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) to take vpon me the defence of this Chriſten man / whom I ſe here accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed to haue deſerued death. Nether do I ſuppoſe it can diſpleaſe you which be Chriſten / that one Chriſten man doth ſhew a Chriſten worke vnto another. For allthough it might be eſtemed a ſtraunge and vn wont thing / that I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vpon me to defende a man / who nether in name ner viſure hath bene knowne vnto me till this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t daye / nether I alſo beyng of his kynne: Yet muſt the band of Chriſten loue be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered / which knytteth and coupleth vnto vs / not onely oure frendes and ſuch as do vs good / but euen oure ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies alſo and them that do vs euell.</p>
            <p>Inſo much that by the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of oure Sauioure / we are bounde with body / goodes and counſail to helpe all men without excepcion / what nede ſo euer they be in. How much leſſe do ye ſuppoſe / that a Chriſten broder is to be forſaken / which ſtondeth in daunger of his life / and that for Chriſtes doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſake / for the which no man (excepte he were farre out of the right waye)
<pb facs="tcp:177901:3"/> dylieuer refuſe to ioperde his nec.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles (Righte deare Iudges) in this company that ſtondeth hereby round aboute vs / mighte doutleſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny be founde / which coulde handle this matter with more apte wordes / with more grauite / conninge and eloquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / then I. To whom I was alſo purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed right gladly with all my hert to ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue place. Notwithſtonding as ye do ſe / amonge this greate multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple / there is yet none founde / that in ſuche a vertuous / fre / honeſt / profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and nedefull matter / wolde laye to his handes. Where as we ſe yet daylie not a ſmal no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre / that willingly / and earneſtly / and with greate diligence doth maynteyne open felonye / wicked periurye / ſhamefull aduoutrie ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous and venymous matters / horrible robbynge / manſlaughter / murthure / and other beaſtly vyces: and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vayne fauoure ſake / or els (which is yet more ſhamefull) for a fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thie rewarde or lucre. Onely this inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent Chriſten man / which for the pure doctryne of Chriſt ſake ſtondeth in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of his life / hath not one / I will not ſaye to manynteyne him / but ſo much as ones to comforte him. Is not this a
<pb facs="tcp:177901:3"/> pitifull caſe? O what a wicked tyme is this? But alas / euen as the vngodlie &amp; wicked are full of malicyous envye / ſo are the ſymple both fear full &amp; ſoone perſuaded.</p>
            <p>As for me / my lordes / I haue not feared to take this matter in hand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confidence in your wiſdome and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe / ſpecially for aſmuch as I conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre it is not nedefull for me to vſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paynted wordes of glorious eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce or vayne appearaunce / which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinh to this matter apperteyneth: for aſmuch as it conſiſteth not in perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion / but in the trueth it ſelfe. It is a fre open matter / and ought alſo frely and openly to be handled. Here muſt be no diſceate / no coloure / no cauillaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / but onely the trueth / which vnto vs in this matter ſhalbe abundaunt and ſufficient. Onely I beſech you ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght worſhipful Iudges / that ye will louyngly / diligently and pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly geue audience. Not that I haue anye ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / as though ye were vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mynded agaynſt this innocent man. For by certayne manifeſt tokens an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euydent ſignes. I haue parceaued all / ready / that ther is not one of you all: which is not mynded to diſcharge him.
<pb facs="tcp:177901:4"/> Not withſtonding I ſuppoſe it ought by al meanes to be auoyded / that men do not thinke / ye haue quytte him mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thoroww fauoure / then by vertue of the lawe.</p>
            <p>For oure aduerſarie in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnte hathe vſed ſuche cauillacion / yea euen for the nones and of ſet purpoſe / and hath myxte ther in ſo many and dyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe vayne and fayned matters: Whiche amonge ſymple people mighte eaſely haue an appearaunce of the veryte / </p>
            <p>That equyte requireth / and neceſſite conſtrayneth me / to confute all ſuch with the trueth and ſubſtanciall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: To the intent that no dubte ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de remayne by anye man. Neuertheles I am not therfore ſo carefull to delyuer this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life / who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I heare defende: Yea he himſelfe for the honoure of Chriſt / yf nede requyre / doth not refuſe to leſe it. The onely doctryne of Chriſt is it / which I wold fayne declare to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemiſhe and vndefyled. The ſame onely / the ſame (I ſaye) haue I taken vpon me to maynteyne. For it am I mynded to do my beſt.</p>
            <p>But now deare iudges a fore I co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to the head articles / I am aduyſed to talke a litle with oure aduerſary.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And now I ſpeake vnto the / in the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh gowne / I meane euen the thou accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer / which / as I heare ſaye / art called an inquiſitour of hereſie. And firſt of all I demaunde of the / what moued the / to take that vn happie officie vpon the? What worſhippe or profit thoughteſt thou to optayne therby. Me thinketh (to ſaye playnlie) thou haſt ſought no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this matter / ſaue onely either filthie lucre / vayne pryde / or wicked ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye: Or happlie thou art ſo ydle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine owne buſynes / that thou canſt handle ſtraunge matters / and ſuch as are no poynt of thy charge: Or els thou art ſo pure and cleare from thine owne vyces / that thou enquyreſt after other mens offences / with ſuch curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / as well beſemeth ſuch an holy Scry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be and erneſt defendoure of the church of Rome. A wonder full holynes vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / yf it be ſo. And the ſame onely thing (I ſuppoſe) is yet lackyng vnto thy perfecte hiolynes / which haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed certeyne innocent Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allready. O how ſwete a doctoure of diuynite is this? Is not this a vertuous defendoure of the church.</p>
            <p>But let vs put the caſe (neuerte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les without preiudice of trueth) that
<pb facs="tcp:177901:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> this man whom thou accuſeſt / be an he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retike / and vtterly no Chriſten. Is it thy mynde / that he ſhal therfore in all the haiſt be ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led vnto the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man / and put to death? dyddeſt thou euer rede / that Chriſt and his diſciples commaundes to ſlaye ſuch as receaued the faith: or that after they had recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it / fell awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it agayne? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe not. Neuertheles thou mighteſt weel haue red / that the vnbeleuers ought ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be inſtructe and taught like as they that are fallen / ought after a brotherly faſhion to behelped vp agayne and exhorted: and that they which of an obſtinate mynde will heare no exhortacion / ouhht to be eſchued &amp; auoyded / but not in all the haiſt put to death. Thou with thy bitter accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacion / thinkeſt to bring this Chriſten man in to daunger of his life. But how farre the ſame thy complaynte is from the wholſome doctryne of Chriſt and his diſciples / mayeſt thou conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Yff thou haddeſt bene mynded to make inquiſicion for hereſie / wherby thou nughteſt helpe thy broder which is fallen and bring him from his erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer vnto the right waye / then were
<pb facs="tcp:177901:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> thy diligence to be commended. But now for aſmuch as thy deſyre is to murther him like a beaſt / thy cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie muſt be reproued. Nether can I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne for what intent thou ſhuldeſt by right condemne him vnto death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it be for ſome other offence then lacke of faith. For either he hath neuer bene a Chriſten man (which were te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arious to affirme / for aſmoch as he was baptiſed in Chriſt / &amp; hath ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt / were of noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubteth) Or els is he fallen awaye from Chriſt / which thou ſhalt neuer be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. Now though thou couldeſt verifie one of theſe two acording to thy myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / yet ſhal it be founde / that thou haſt wrongfully accuſed him to haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued death.</p>
            <p>Yf one ſhulde accuſe a Iewe at the lawe that he were worthy to dye / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he holdeth nothinge of Chriſt / wolde not euery one ſaye / that he we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re a madde man? Not that I wil excuſe the wicked infidelite of a Iewe. But becauſe that in this caſe / the iudgment appreteyneth not vnto man / but muſt be referred vnto god. There dwel Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes now alſo in many partes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome / not onely in ſafegarde / but
<pb facs="tcp:177901:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> occupie alſo / and that openly.</p>
            <p>As for the Turkes which of a very vnſatiable gredynes towarde tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye / vexe vs horribly and all that we haue / yea ſpare no maner of age ner kynde / No man iudgeth it wronge to deſtroye them in battayll. But to mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thur their wifes and children becauſe they beleue not in Chriſt / do I take for a very beeſtly thinge: And ſpecially out of warre in the tyme of peace / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Turkes them ſelues / in matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernyng the faith / are nothinge cruell agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>It is not mete / to make a deuorce of mariage / for only vnbeleues ſake: ſo long as the vnbeleuyng huſband refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to dwell with the beleuynge wife / nether as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as the vnbeleuyng wife reſuſeth not to dwell with te bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. A Chriſten ſeruant is bounde to rendre to his vnbeleuynge maſter his due obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; that not to the eye ſight / but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hert / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yf he ſerued Chriſt himſelfe: Much leſſe than ſhal he take a pon him to haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to hurte him. And thou thinkeſt that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to be ſlayne / to whoſe charge thou canſt laye no thinge ſaue onely enfidelite. Madd and vndiſcrete art thou / Yf thou ſo beleueſt: Yea deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate
<pb facs="tcp:177901:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> and vngodly / Yf thou beleueſt no ſuch thinge / &amp; yet wilt thou perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de other men / to bring this innocent in ioperdye of his life. Notwithſton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng I know allready / what thou wilt ſaye therto.</p>
            <p>I accuſe no Iewe (wilt thou ſaye) no Turke / no heithen: What haue we to do with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are with oute as. S Paul ſaieth. I do accuſe a rennagate and Apoſtata: who though he be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in Chriſt / and louyngly receaued in to the wombe of oure mother the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly church / yet thorow the counſaill of the deuel / hath he not bene aſhamed to fall from the right faifh and to cleue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to certeyne mens hereſies / agaynſt the cammaundement of the church: Nother was he therwith ſatiſfied / but thorow his falſe perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath he gone aboute to bringe many moo / euen in to ſuch like errous. Such one / as I ſuppoſe / ough to be hewen off from the body / as a corrupte membre: to the intent that the ſore frett no farther.</p>
            <p>Haue I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thy mynde? Thou haſt nodded with thy heade. I perceaue that I haue not geſſed amyſſe. Now well tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / thou graunteſt that he is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in Chriſt and louyngly receaued in to the wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of oure mother the holy
<pb facs="tcp:177901:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> church I deſire nomore. Thou art gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt ſteppe that tow ſtodeſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherby I hope / that vpon the other ſteppe wheron thou now ſtondeſt / thou wilt not longe contynue.</p>
            <p>With few / but with true reaſons now haue I declared vnto the allrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / that one which was neuer no Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten / ought not to be ſlayne for onely vnbeleues ſake / without other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But now wil I brefely ſhewe the what I ſuppoſe ought to be done with ſuch as are Chriſtened / and yet tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row hereſie and errours concernyng faith / or thorow other ſynne and vyce / are fallen from Chriſt. For Chriſt is two maner of wayes denyed / not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with worde / but alſo with dede / whyle there be many / that are euer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ady to praiſe Chriſt with their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and yet in their dedes are ſo open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agaynſt him / that therby it maye be eaſely perceaued / that / excepte the vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne bare wordes / they haue no Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poynt in them. Yf thou now haſt taken vpon the / at the Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeate of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawe to accuſe all ſuch as vnchriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as verely they be in dede / whan ſhal thy accuſacion then and complynte ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue an end? Yf thou meaneſt / that they
<pb facs="tcp:177901:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ought immendialy to be ſlayne as ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as they fall / what place then ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce haue? Who ſhall haue ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure than to do penaunce / or to ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de?</p>
            <p>Wilt thou alſo be ſo ſhameleſſe / as to denye forgyueneſſe of ſynnes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that truly amende? Or canſt thou be ſo cruell / that thou wilt loke for no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion / But immediatly deſtroye the man boeth body and ſoule? Hou canſt thou knowe (thou vnreaſonable man) wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / how / or by what meane / god as a mercifull father / wil call ſynners agayne vnto true faith and repentaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / who vpon Peters queſtion / com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund him to forgeue his neghboure ſeuen and ſeuentie tymes? Beleueſt thou him to be ſo vnmercifull / that what he commaundeth a man to do / he will denye the ſame / to ſuch as praye vnto him? Awaye / awaye I ſaye with this thy vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and blaſphemous opynion. God ſaieth: I wil not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ath ofſymer / but rather that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and lyue. Thou cryeſt: An heretike ought to be brent. And why ſo I praye the? leſt he ſhulde conuerte / and ſo lyue. With this voyce diſcouereſt thou thy ſelfe allready / that thou art achilde of the deuel / which is amurthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb facs="tcp:177901:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the bekynnyng. I preceaue thou haſt chaunged thy colou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re for veri anger. I haue touched thy holyneſſe to ſore. Perdon me yf I haue done amyſſe I wold haue dealth more frendly with the / yf thou with this thy vndiſcrete and vnreaſonable accuſation / haddeſt not be wrayed thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But leſt thou ſhuldeſt thinke that I fauoure ſuch as denye Chriſt in worde or dede / or ſuch as blaſpheme god / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng oft exhorted / well &amp; truly taught / yea conuycte with ſubſtanciall reaſons out of the ſcripture / &amp; yet will neuer le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue their vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and falſe opynio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: leſt thou ſhuldeſt thinke (I ſaye) that I fauoured any ſuch / I wil declare myne opynion / &amp; that not out of myne owne brayne / but ſuch an opynion as is paſt all dowte / certeyne and ſure / yea euen ſpoken by the holy mouth of Chriſt him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Yf hewill not heare the church (ſaieth Chriſt) than counte him as an heithen and open ſynner. Hath not Chriſt with theſe wordes declared / that ſcuh as are diſhobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto his church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacion / ought to be excluded from the felaſhippe of the good? Why lacheſt thou ſo hartely / as though it were but
<pb facs="tcp:177901:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> a trifle a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be excluded from the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſhippe of ſayntes? Me thyinkeh thou woteſt not well what matter it maketh / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the auctorite of the keyes / one is ſeparated out of the church. Vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I ſaye vnto you (ſaieth the lorde) what ſoeuer ye bynde vpon erth / ſhal alſo be bound in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo / there haſt thou no vayne opynion / but an aſſured iudge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mt out of the mouth of oure Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure himſelfe.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtel Paul co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth to eſchue an heretike / after that he is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warned. And the man which kepte his ſtepmother / delyuereth he vnto the deuell that the ſprete maye be ſaued at the latterdaye. Dyd he therfore conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him vnto death / becauſe he wrythet to delyuer him vnto Satan / to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the fleſh. That be farre from the ecxellent loue of Paul / that he wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de not rather helpe vp a brother that we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re fallen / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vtterly to caſt him a awye? The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo of the matter / which folowed therof / declareth it ſelfe / that he meant not to haue him ſlayne / but to haue him pourged out as an old leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the intent that he ſhulde not ſowre the whole lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe of dow / and that at the laſt he might amende / as he dyd in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de.
<pb facs="tcp:177901:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> For in the ſeconde Epiſtole to the Corinthians he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth / that for aſmuch as the ſame man came to know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege and repentaunce / they ſhulde vith all louynge kyndneſſe take him vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne / forgeue him his offence / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte him in his heuynes / leſt he ſhulde be ſwalowed on (or fall in deſpayre) thorow ouer much ſorowe. All which thinges coulde not haue come to pas / yf the man in all the haiſt had afore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne preuented with death. O the right godly pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuffringe of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Sauioure / who as a god ſhepherde leauynge the nyne &amp; nyentie ſhepe in the wilderniſſe / ſeketh it that is loſt: not to caſt it vnto the wolffe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured / but louyngly to bring it agayne in to his ſhepe folde.</p>
            <p>Now vnderſtondeſt thou / that my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne opinion (yea the opynion of Chriſt) is confirmed with ſcriptures / with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples and by Paul him ſelfe. Nether can it helpe the / though thou obiecteſt vnto me the parable of the goſpell / wher in the houſholder commaundeth his ſtewarde to hew downe the vnfru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull tre / yf it bringe no more frute. For ſuch knowledge of tyme muſt one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be refered vnto god / as vnto him
<pb facs="tcp:177901:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> that onely knoweth the hertes of all men. Els had noc Chriſt forbydden to plucke vp the wedes afore the harueſt.</p>
            <p>Yet muſt I declare vnto the / what bodely hinderaunce muſt growe and folowe out of this ſentence of excomu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicacion / to him that is conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned ther in: leſt thou ſhuldeſt thinke my myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de were to iudge no forther / but with bare wordes onely to haue him exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyon of the Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Thou haſt hearde the fearfull thon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bolt of oure Sauioure: what ſo euer ye bynde vpon earth / ſhal alſo be bound in heauen. Thus is he then all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready put out of the boke of life / and lyuinge dead. Beleue me / it is an heuye puniſhment. I wote not where to fynde a ſorer. But they that in their hartes are more moued with wordly matters / let them heare this that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>All honeſt vertuous perſonnes ſhal eſchue him. Howbeit ſuch a one as hath ſo denyed Chriſt / that he hath alſo caſt from him all ſham faſtneſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty / might peraduenture not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care therfore. From all worſhipe (yf he were in anye) and worſhipfull offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhal he be depoſed. All Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:177901:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> abhorre him / and erneſtly hate his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delite / and yet loue his parſone / as it becometh the diſciples of Chriſt: to the intent it maye appeare / that ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is layed vpon him / not of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyce or euell will / but done all to the intent / that he thorow ſuch temporall correction / might conuerte / and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued vnto Chriſt the lorde for euer.</p>
            <p>Haue I ſayde ynough now to thy crue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite with this my declaracion? Or is not this ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? Take hede / I aduyſe the / that in iudging other men to ſore-thou condemne not thy ſelfe. For I truſt I will ſhortly bringe to pas / that it ſhalbe manifeſt and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto euery man / hou that thou thy ſelfe art euen te ſame he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike / to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the forſayde puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by right and reaſon belongeth.</p>
            <p>Now turne I me agayne vnto you (Right prudent iudges) hauyng no ſmall confidence in youre ſyngular worſhipe and grauyte / foraſmuch as I knowe that ye will geue no ſentence / but ſuch as accordeth with equyte / and ſerueth to the honoure of Chriſt: yea right glad I am to ſe / that the ſame lieth now in youre auctorite.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I purpoſe not to hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de you vp long with vayne wordes / I
<pb facs="tcp:177901:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> will now come to the matter / which I ſuppoſe concerneth not onely him that here ſtondeth vpon life and death / but euery one of vs alſo that ſeke the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of Chriſt. I will bring in no new thing / or that hitherto hath not bene heard. For in this matter / wher we haue now continually go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aboute more then twentie yeares / what can be ſpakon that hath not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne offt ſpoken afore? What can be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned / that hath not affore bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ached openly / and (as they ſaye) vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe toppes? I ſuppoſe it not nedefull to teach you in this matter / but onely to put you in remembraunce and to exhorte you? Wherfore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche you / ye will but euen paciently heare me / acording as ye haue hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to done alreadye.</p>
            <p>I perceaue (right deare iudges) that oure aduerſary hat grounded his whole accuſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that he will ſaye: how that this Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man is fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Chriſten church. Wherfore I ſe well / I muſt firſt e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deuoure my ſelfe to declare vnto you the true deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church. Which yf it be well knowne &amp; vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / I perceaue that all the reſt maye lightly be diſcuſſed / and preadue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture the ſooner brought to an end.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>As touching this: we beleue an holy Chatolike or generall churche / which is the feloſhhippe of ſaynctes. Here ye ſe (righ deare iudges) with how few wordes the true deſcription of the church is ſet forth before oure eyes.</p>
            <p>Wherby we maye euidently percaue / that the holy Catholike church is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but a feloſhippe of ſaynctes. And the ſame is alſo the bryde of Chriſt without ſpot or wrynckle / purified thorow the bloude of the brydgrome himſelfe: euen the heauenly hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem / in to the which / no vncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone commeth: the moſt holy temple / wher into is entred oure biſhope Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt / who is a preſt for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ordre of Melchiſedech. This I ſaye / is the church buylded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / agaynſt the which nether the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ner the waues of waters / no ner the gates of hell / ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preuayle: the head and fundacio wheoff is Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
            <p>To this church pertayne all they / that ſyns the begynnyng of the worlde haue bene ſaued / and that ſhalbe ſaued vnto the ende therof. For they are the lyuinge ſtones of this heauenly hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem and of this moſt holy temple.</p>
            <p>Know ye not (ſaieth. S. Paul) that
<pb facs="tcp:177901:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> ye are the tempel of God / and that the ſprete of god dwelleeh in you? Yf anye man defyle this temple / him ſhal god deſtroye: for the temple of god is holy / the ſame temple are ye.</p>
            <p>Euen this church / doth this Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brother of oures beleue ſtedfaſtly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yea and in this church alſo beleueth he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyueneſſe of ſynnes / ond after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the fleſh an euerlaſting li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. Why ſaieſt thou than / that he is fale<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len awaye from the church? To the ſpeake I now / thou vnreaſonable accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer: What haſt thou yet more to laye to his charge? He beleueth in god the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther allmightie maker of heauen and arth / and in Ieſu Chriſt his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne oure lorde / which was conceaued of the holy gooſt / borne of Marye the virgyn / ſuffred vnder Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate / was crucified / dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried / deſcended vnto hell / on the thirde daye roſe agayne from death / aſcended vnto heauen / ſitteth at the right hand of god the father allmightye / from thence ſhal he come to iudge the quyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke an dead. He beleueth alſo in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gooſt / and al the reſt that we mencio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned afore of the church. He beleueth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiwiſe all that is written by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes
<pb facs="tcp:177901:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> and other olde fathers of the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de teſtament. In like maner beleueth he all that in the goſpels is written of the actes and doctryne of Chriſt. He confeſſeth alſo that the doctryne of the Apoſtles and diſciples of Chriſt is not to be dowted vpon. Moreouer he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth that whatſoeuer the holy fathers of the new teſtament haue written / is true / ſo farre as it is not contrary to the doctryne of Chriſt and of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</p>
            <p>With this true and fre confeſſion of faith / I ſuppoſe thou art ſo ſatiſfied / that now thou wilt not ſticke with all expedicion to quyte this Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and faithfully to commytte him vnto the iudges as a right membre of the church: and for aſmuch as thou haſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduyſedly accuſed him as an heretike and as a rennegate from the church / &amp; haſt done him wrong / I hope thou wilt therfore aſke him forgeueneſſe. But I ſe well / thou ſhakeſt thy heade / byteſt thy tethe one vpon another / and art be come (as me thinketh) nothing the myl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der. Wherfore beholde I beſech you / how ſhameles this man is / yf I maye call ſuch one a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which ſo vnma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aleth / that I ſuppoſe he hath forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he himſelfe is a man. I doute not right deare Iudges / but the ſame fre confeſſion of this Chriſten man is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient ynough to quyte him / and that in youre iudgment he neadeth no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther clearyng of himſelfe. Notwithſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding leſt oure aduerſary ſhulde repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / that I haue ſayde nothing to the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely rehearſall of his accuſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tingly paſſed ouer it: or how that I am ſo ſhort of memorye / that I haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what he hath layed for him ſelfe: therfore wil I rehearce it all agayne: to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue repeted his vnhoneſt complaynt / and confuted it / euery man maye vnderſtond / that he is ſmytten with his owne ſwerd. Ye haue perceaued / I ſuppoſe / that his whole ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſacion conſiſted in eight principall ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticles / which I will now repete in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre / that yf any thing ther in haue bene forgetten / it maye be called vnto rema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce agayne.</p>
            <p>This heretike (ſaith oure aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary) doth affirme.</p>
            <p>Firſt / that the biſhope of Rome is not the head of the church ner the true vycar of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly: that the maſſe is no ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ner ought to be vſed for other.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thirdly: that the ſupper of the lordt ought to be myniſtred in fourmes both of bread and wyne / and that alſo vnto the laye people.</p>
            <p>Fourthly: that ther is no purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / and that ſuffragies for the deed are in vayne / and ſuperſticious.</p>
            <p>Fyfthly: that it is not neceſſary to call vpon ſaynctes.</p>
            <p>Sixthly: that auricular confeſſion was nether commaunded ner inſtitute of Chriſt and his diſciples.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly: that on the daies prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited and forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / it is no ſynne to eate fleſh.</p>
            <p>Eightely / and fynally / he ſaieth plane<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / that preſtes maye mary.</p>
            <p>Theſe (ye deare Iudges) are the fou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le miſdedes: theſe are the horrible vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: theſe are the deteſtable blaſphemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es: her off cometh the great vproure &amp; horrible noyſe of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and erthe / wher thorow it is to be feared / that the fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re elementes wil come together / and that rhe world wil returne in to his ol darcknes and confuſion agayne.</p>
            <p>And why do not we all rent oure clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes / and ſtoppe oure eares after the maner of the Iewes / &amp; crie ewith lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de voyce? He hath blaſphemed: Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie / Crucifie. Such a matter might
<pb facs="tcp:177901:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> happly be laught at / yf it were ſhewed in the waye of ieaſting / and to make the people a paſtyme with all. But for aſmuch as the matter is now handled in Iudgment / and brought ſo farre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth / that this Chriſten man is like to ſuffre death therfore / Me thinketh euery faithfull Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ground of his hert to bewayle it.</p>
            <p>But now let vs examen the firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle / and pondre well / what is to be holden of the biſhoope of Romes po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer. All Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men do confeſſe / that the holy Catholike (or vniuerſal) church / is the feloſhippe of ſaynctes.</p>
            <p>And this is the one onely church / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin is but one lorde / one faith / one baptyme / one god and father of all thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. But for aſmuch as we ſaye: I bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue an holy vniuerſall church / we do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe / that the ſame is not viſible ner corporall. Notwithſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / ther is named yet another church which is bothe viſible and corporall.</p>
            <p>Whervnto the keyes of the kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of heauen are committed / which the lord alſo meaneth whan he ſaieth: Tell it vnto the church. In the which church all they are comprehended / that are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſten / good and euell / wherin alſo the tares groweth with the wheate
<pb facs="tcp:177901:14"/> vntill the tyme of the harueſt.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles this is not an one onely church / but deſtributed in to many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: for it were vnpoſſible to haue / in one place an one onely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all Chriſten together / ſeyng they dwell ſo farre one from another / &amp; be of ſo ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie lanhages &amp; maners. Therfore the Apoſtles as we do rede / haue in all par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ordyned as many churches / as they thought neceſſary acording to the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of the countrees: And gaue vnto euery church their peculiar biſhoppe / to kepe the lordes flocke: whom the alſo called preſt or elder: geuyng them a tyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le of reputacion / either becauſe of their age / or by reaſon of their excellent gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyte &amp; vertuous conuerſacion. To ſuch men was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted the care of Chriſtes flock and the myniſtracion of gods wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / to rule the people / and to fede the flock of Chriſt with all.</p>
            <p>As for hye biſhope / vnder Chriſt they knew none. They had al like auctorite. Euery one had the ouerſight of the flock that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto him. But wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anye doubte aroſe / they vſed not to ſhew it vnto one alone as to the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad / or to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all (which was vnpoſſible) but vnto certeyne: who whan they had called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of the lorde / knew in
<pb facs="tcp:177901:14"/> the holy gooſt / what was to be done / as we maye openly ſe in the Actes of the Apoſtles. Wherfore me thinketh it a great wonder that euer the church of Rome came in ſuch reputation / that it hath hither to bene taken of many for the head of all churches / yea for the one onely Catholike or vniuerſall church: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that in holy ſcripture it hath no teſtimonye that maye truly be alled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged to any ſuch purpoſe. For we haue declared now allready / that ther is not one onely viſible church: which thing appeareth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly out of the wordes of Chriſt / whan he ſaieth tell it vnto the church. Shulde he now runne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem vnto Rome / to tell his brothers faulte? Therfore be there many chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacions / wherin the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of god in this vayle of miſery are myxte amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the deuel / which inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo they daylie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne of</p>
            <p>But let vs ſe with what reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauillacions / oure aduerſary goeth aboute to maynteyne this his Romſhe church / &amp; his grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſyre pope or biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe of Rome. We reade in the goſpell / that Chriſt aſked his diſciples: who ſaye ye that I am? Peter anſuered &amp; ſayde: thou art the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the lyuinge god.</p>
            <p>Whervpon Ieſus ſayde vnto him.
<pb facs="tcp:177901:15"/> Bleſſed art thou Simon Ionas ſonne / for fleſhe and bloude hath not opened that vnto the / but my father which is in heauen. And I ſaye vnto the: Thou art Petrus (that is / apperteyning to the ſtonye rocke) and vpon this rocke will I buylde my church / and the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of hell ſhal not preuayle agaynſt it. And I will geue the the keyes of the kyng ome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; what ſoeuer thou byndeſt vpon erthe / ſhal alſo be bounde in heauen: And what ſoeuer thou loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt vpon erthe / ſhal be looſed alſo in heauen.</p>
            <p>This promes of Chriſt / which we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo beleue ſtedfaſtly to be fulfilled / ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth oure aduerſary vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to wraiſt vnto his opynion. How now (ſaieth he) dyd not Chriſt playnlie ſaye: Thou art Petrus / and vpon this rock wil I buylde my church: and I will geue the the keyes of the kyngdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen?</p>
            <p>Who I praye the / denyeth that the church is buylded vpon a ſtrong rocke? who will not graunt / that the keyes were committed vnto Peter? Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles we will ſeke the true vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this promes. Whan Peter had conſeſſed Chriſt to be the ſonne of the
<pb facs="tcp:177901:15"/> lyuinge god / the lordt ſayd vnto him: bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas / for fleſhe and bloud hath not opened that vnto the but my father which is in heauen. Wherby Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the gifte of god / and commeth of the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of heauen. Now foloweth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for the faithers ſake: and I ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the / that thou art Petrus / here ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he him another name / not Simon Ionas ſonne / but Petrus / as one that cleueth or belongeth vnto the rocke.</p>
            <p>And vpon this rocke (ſaieth he) wil I buylde my church: as though he ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſaye: bleſſed art thow / for aſmuch as thorow gods reuelacion / thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeſt / that I am the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of the lyuynge god. And therfore art thou Petrus / that is / thou belongeſt vnto the rocke. And vpon this rocke whervnto thou eleueſt now by thy confeſſion / wil I buylde my church. For where as the church of god was noriſhed firſt in hope of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to come / and after that the lawe came as a ſcoolmaſter / ſtode much in outward ceremonies and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the lawe: now that the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte tyme is come / I wil buylde my church vpon my ſelfe / as on the ſtrong rock that whoſoeuer beleueth in me / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:16"/> ſhal not periſhe / but haue euerlaſting li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe. Yf he had ſayde Super Petrum / it might happlie haue bene vnderſtonde of Peter: but ſeyng he ſaieth Super haue petram / we will ſearch the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / whether this rock maye ſignifie anye thing els ſaue onely Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>It is written: beholde / I laye in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſtombling ſtone / and a rocke that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe offended at. And whoſoeuer beleueth on him / ſhal not be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: which ſcripture Paul and Peter al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo declare in maner with the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. And in another place ſaieth Paul? they dranke al of the ſpirituall rocke that folowed them / which rocke was Chriſt. And in the Actes of the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: this is the ſtone that was refuſed of you buylders / and is become the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad couer ſtone / / nether is ther ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in anye other. Loo / here is a true &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient interpretacion of this rocke.</p>
            <p>For as the Apoſtel Paul ſaieth: no man can laye another fundacion then that is layde all ready / namely Chriſt Ieſus. This much haue I ſayd tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the fundacion of the church.</p>
            <p>Now will we come to the keies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:16"/>
            <p>And I (ſaieth the lorde) wil geue the the keies of the kyngdome of heauen. The ſtorie now of the goſpell decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth / that this auctorite of the keies / was not geuen onely vnto Peter / but vnto all the Apoſtles alyke. And whan he had ſo ſpokon (ſaieth the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt) brethed he vpon them / and ſayde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> receaue ye the holy goſt. Whoſe ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ye forgeue / to them are they forge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen: and whoſe ſynnes ye reteyne / to them are they reteyned. Theſe are other wordes / then the lorde ſpake afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re vnto Peter alone / and yet is it all one meanyng. For what this bynding els ſaue onely reteyning of ſynnes?</p>
            <p>And what eles is looſyng / ſaue onely remytting of ſynnes? Wherfore not onely Peter / but al diſciples al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo yea al ſuch as haue the holy gooſt / haue fre autorite to vſe the keyes.</p>
            <p>Yet hath oure aduerſary one reeſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wher by he thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keth to proue that Chriſt gaue the ſuperiorite vnto Peter / na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lye becauſe that in the end of. S. Ihons goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell / the lorde Ieſus ſayde vnto him.</p>
            <p>Symon Ioannes / loueſt thou me more then theſe? Peter anſuered him: yea lorde thou knoweſt that I loue the.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:17"/>
            <p>Ieſus ſayd vnto him: fede my ſhepe / &amp; that ſame ſpake he thre tymes. Out of this will oure aduerſary conclude / that the whole flock of Chriſt was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Peter to be fed: and becauſe the lorde ſayd I haue prayed for the that thy faith fayle not / he will that we ſhal therby vnderſtonde the church of Rome. Yf he now will haue that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde of the church of Rome / as of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters habitacion to come / then out of Chriſtes commaundment which folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth immediatly after / let him lerne / that vnto the church of Rome ther was geuen no preemynence more then to other churches / but that there is equali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. And thou (ſaieth Chriſt) whan thou art conuerted / ſtrength thy brethren: he ſaieth not / ſtrength thy ſhepe / as the chefe ſhepherde: nether thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern / as the moſt holy father) but ſtrength thy brethren. And as oft as ther aroſe any contencion among the diſciples for the ſuperiorite / Chriſt all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye rebuked them / and ſayde / that they were brethren. Therfore ſaieth- S. Paul alſo: vnto euery one of vs is geuen grace acording vnto the meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of the gifte of Chriſt. And immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly after it foloweth: and he himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:177901:17"/> made ſome Apoſtles / ſome prophetes / ſome Euangeliſtes / ſome ſhepherdes and teachers / to the edifie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / to the worke &amp; miniſtracion. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In this rehearſall of miniſtracions / where nameth he one of them to be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad among the Apoſtles? What is beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the name of the chefe ſhepherde? It foloweth alſo: let vs folowe the trueth in loue / and in all thinges gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we in him which is the head / euen Chriſt. Here ſe we that all ſayntes are membres of one body / whoſe head is Chriſt himſelfe. Nether is here menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made of any other head. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſaieth Paul: they which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſom what and greate / added nothing vnto me. But contrarywiſe whan they ſawe / that the goſpell ouer the vncircunciſion was committed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peter (for he that was mightie in Peter in the Apoſtelſhippe one the circunciſion / the ſame was mightie in me amonge the heithen) whan the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that was geuen vnto me / then Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes / Cephas and Ihon / which ſewed to be pylours / gaue vnto me and Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas the right handes of that feloſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe? that we ſhulde be Apoſtles amonge the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and they in the circunciſoo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:18"/>
            <p>What can be founde more playne? S. Paul ſaieth / that he had commiſſion of the Apoſtelſhippe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as Peter had among the circumciſion. Thus after oure aduerſaries doctryne / we muſt haue two heades / ard two che<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe ſhepherdes: the one amonge the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / the other omong the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And why do not the Romaynes boaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of. S. Paul / whom euery man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth an Apoſtel of the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come? But let them heare the reſt of the texte / where it ſayeth that Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Cephas and Ihon ſemed to be py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. Why calleth he Cephas or Peter a pyloure like the other? Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth not he calle him the foundacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church? Why nameth he him not the chefe among the Apoſtles? They gaue me (ſaieth he) and Barnaba the right hand of that feloſhippe. Here he affirmeth / that they were receaued of them as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panyons. All which thinges declare no ſuperiorite / but a brotherly equalite among the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>But let vs graunt / that Peter was the chefe among the Apoſtles / the che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſhepherde of the lordes flock / and the true vycare of Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth (though we nede none ſuch / for aſmuch as
<pb facs="tcp:177901:18"/> Chriſt hath promiſed vs to be with vs vnto the end of the world / nether is his kyngdome of this world) but put the caſe that it ſo is / why will the biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome yet vſe any ſuch tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le? What excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thing ſoeuer was in Peter / that ſame receaued he at the gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of god thorow his faith &amp; loue. The ſame grace lacked not Paul &amp; the other Apoſtles: for though Peters ſhadow dyd heale many / yet helped Pauls nap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyn not a fen thorow like working of the lorde / which confirmed his worde with ſuch tokens. But what is that to the biſſhopes of Rome? Doth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me proue / that Peter &amp; Paul preached at Rome: As for Peter it is not very certeyne that euer he came there. But let vs graunt that he was at Rome / &amp; biſſhope there alſo. Shal therfore all the biſſhoppes of Rome comming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter / inheret likewiſe the grace that Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter had? O how bleſſed an eſtate hath the biſſhope of Rome / yf euen the ſame grace of god that was in Peter / be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to his office? Yf he might inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret the faith &amp; loue of Peter / doutles he ſhulde alſo opteyne like grace. But euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth / that theſe thinges were giſtes of grace in Peter and in the other Apoſtles / conſideringe that
<pb facs="tcp:177901:19"/> vertues or vyces come not to inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: But euery ſoule that ſynneth / the ſame ſhall dye: vertue alſo doth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome take place in the ſucceſſours.</p>
            <p>Why do the Romiſhe than boaſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ſo ſore? Do thei it onely becauſe that Prter was at Rome? That were euen as yf a ſhoomaker dwelling in a houſe (wherin a great lerned man dwelt ſomtyme) wolt boaſt himſelfe to haue opteyned ſome ſciences of his pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deceſſoure by reaſon of that dwellyng place. Yea it were euen as yf a poore fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low entring in to an office / wherin had bene a riche man afore (to whom greate dettes were owinge / not concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng the office) wol requyre of dewtie the ſame his predeceſſours dettes / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſuccedeth him in the office Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like argumentes in a maner doth oure aduerſary vſe / wherby he goeth aboute to make the biſſhope of Rome like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Peter in auctorite. Peter / ſaieth he was ordened chefe ſhepherde of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes flock: to him were committed the keyes of the kyngdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And the ſame Peter was ſomtyme biſſhope of Rome / therfore all biſſhopes of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / are the chefe ſhepherdes and haue the keyes of the kyngdome of heauen.
<pb facs="tcp:177901:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Though this be but a ſmall argument / yet hath god permitted that thorow the craffte of the deuel / it is ſo ſuncke in to many mens myndes / that who ſo euer vndertaketh but with a worde to do ought ther agaynſt / muſt ſtonde in daunger of his life. Now is it manifeſt that for the mayntenaunce of his opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion / he (namely oure aduerſary hath nothinge / excepte we graunt him / that Peter was biſhope of Rome. Yf that now alone be ſufficient for the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of ſuch exceadinge greate auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / I referre it to the diſcretion of you that be Iudges. Now will we ſpeake of the maſſe.</p>
            <p>This name Maſſe / was doutleſſe in the Apoſtles tyme nether vſed ner he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardof. Nether can there any certeyne occaſion be ſhewed whence this name ſhuld come. But certeyne it is / that all the preparacion aboute it / was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and ordened to the intent / that the ſupper and death of the lorde might be had in remembraunce: which maye eaſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly be perceaued by the veſtimentes and other thinges perteyning to the maſſe. Now in the prymityue church was not the ſupper of the lorde kepte afore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / as now the vſe is / but in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng
<pb facs="tcp:177901:20"/> after ſupper as Chriſt himſefe kepte it. Neuertheles thorow the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaueouae of certeyne filthie perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / which with their dronkennes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured this holy ſupper / aroſe great ſlaunder and offence / which. S. Paul to the Corinthians doth erneſtly rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke. And therfore thought the holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it ſhulde not be agaynſt the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of the lorde. Yf men kepte this holy ſupper afo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oone / faſting: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by ſuch inordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e people might ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what be withdrawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience. Which the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidred / thei might well do / for aſmuch as they altred no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the principall matter.</p>
            <p>And at the firſt / was no more added thervnto / ſaue onely the Pater noſter / the prayer of the lorde. But afterward in proces of tyme by addyng more and more it grew tho the poynt that it is now at. And beſydes that with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions they thought to garniſhe the ſupper of the lorde (peraduenture of a good intent) they haue allmoſt vtterly loſt the principall poyntes of the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the ſupper. So that now the right name of it is altred / and no more called the lordes ſupper / but is called
<pb facs="tcp:177901:20"/> Meſſe / which name is both ſtraunge and vnknowne in the ſcripture: yea and that worſe is / it is named a ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / that maye be done for other folkes. Wherof then ſpronge the ſlaunderous market of byeng and ſellyng of maſſes in churches: here of was renewed the daungerous ydolatrie / that we ranne vnto the maſſe as to a ſpeciall worck / thinkyng there to fetch all ſaluacion / which we ſhulde haue loked for onely at Chriſtes hande.</p>
            <p>But let vs loke / wherfore they call it a ſacrifice. Euen becauſe (ſaie they) that in the maſſe / Chriſt the ſonne is offred vp vnto god his father. O what a greate blaſphemy is this / yea to be ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horred of al vertuous men. Who wold thinke it poſſible / that men mortall and ſynfull / coulde euer haue bene ſo in a lapert or rather mad / as to preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with their vncleane handes / to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre Chriſt the lorde vnto his father yet ones agayne? Chriſt (ſaieth. S. Paul) is entred in to the very heauen / for to appeare now in the ſight of god for vs: not to offre himſelfe offten / as the hye preſt entreth in to the holy place eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare with ſtraunge bloude:
<pb facs="tcp:177901:21"/> for then muſt he haue offt ſuffred ſens the world beganne. And afterward it foloweth: thus was Chriſt offred vp ones for all to take awaye the ſynnes of many: but they will ſaye: Chriſt is not ſo ſacrificed in the maſſe / that he dieth agayne vpon the croſſe / but it is for the remembraunce of the ſame ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice that ones was made. Whi do they than call it a ſacrifice / ſeyng it is but a remembraunce of a ſacrifice? And why ſaie they that it maye be done for other ſeyng that of it ſelfe it is no ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / but onely a remembraunce of the ſupper and paſſion of oure lordt Ieſu Chriſt? Which ſaieth: take and eate / this is my body. And of the cuppe he ſaieth: drynke ye all therout. And as afft as ye this do / then do it to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of me. He ſaieth not offre my body and my bloude. Wherfore let the rihht &amp; true remembraunce of the lordes Supper remayne in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacions / and let vs ſhew the lordes death vntill he come.</p>
            <p>Now yf we be diſpoſed to offre / let vs offre oure owne bodies / a quycke / holy and acceptable ſacrifice vnto god / which is euen the reaſonable waye to ſerue him. We reade in the ſcripture / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> that no vyce was poniſhed ſo ſore / as the abuſe of gods ſeruyce. Wherfore me thinketh all vertuous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tely praye / that the abuſe of the maſſe were put downe in the churches. For yf we wilfully ſynne after the knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of the trueth / there remayneth no mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſacrifice for ſynnes. &amp;c.? But I willet the maſſe go / and treate of both the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des in the lordes holy Supper / whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhulde alſo be geuen vnto the laye people.</p>
            <p>It is paſt all doubte by euery man / that Chriſt in the holy Supper gaue his diſciples both the kyndes. Therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it is manifeſt / that their opynion is not euell / which wolde haue the chalice diſtributed vnto euery man. And me thinketh the other do erre ſore / that holde the contrary / and ſpecially becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe they put ſuch difference betwene pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes and laye people / not conſideryng the preſtly office that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vnto all faithfull beleuers. For in the lawe of Moſes / the office of preſtes was to offre and praye for the pople. But now for aſmuch as Chriſt beyng ones offred vp for vs / hath abrogate all other ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / and not onely permitted but alſo commaunded all men to praye: I can
<pb facs="tcp:177901:22"/> not ſewhat difference can be betwene preſtes and laye people / excepte the go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uernaunce of the church and minyſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of gods worde. For. S. Peter in his Epiſtel ſaieth: and ye alſo as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtones / are made a ſpirituall hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / an holy preſthode / to offre vp ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſacrifices / acceptable to god tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt. And euen there alſo ſaieth. S. Peter: but ye are the cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen generacion / the royall preſthode / the holy nacion. etc. Here wryteth. S. Peter not onely vnto biſhoppes and preſtes / but to the ſtraungers that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re diſperſed and ſcatred abrode in Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to / Galatia etc. And calleth them alltogether an holy and royall preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode.</p>
            <p>S. Paul alſo wryting of this holy ſupper of the lorde to the commen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacions at Corinthum / maketh mencion not onely of the bred / but alſo of the cupen. Yf the cuppe then at that tyme / was commen vnto all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men / why is it now withdrawen from the laye people?</p>
            <p>The holy fathers (ſaieth oure aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary haue with good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce brought the ſupper to this ordenyng that it
<pb facs="tcp:177901:22"/> now is in: and that mihht they well do / as we reade that in the Apoſtles tyme certeyne thinges were ordyned / wher of no mencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in the goſpell. Among which this is one in the Actes of the Apoſtles / where they commaunded to abſteyne from thinges offred vnto Idol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / and from bloude and from ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: whiche commaundement the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles eſtemed neceſſary. Whervnto I anſwere brefely / that the Apoſtles ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no ſuch commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that it ſhulde allwaye ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynue / ſeynge they them ſelues afterward kep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it not. Neuertheles they hauynge reſpecte vnto the tyme / thought to avoyde the offendyng of the weake. But whan the goſpel was more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye come to light / they ceaſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch commaundmentes as thinges not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary the verite beyng knowne. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of this occaſion dyd Paul circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe Timothy / wher as neuertheles afterward whan the Iewes wolde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue had him to circumcyſe Titus alſo / he wold not geue place vnto them one houre. Euen ſo me thenketh ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de it he now likewiſe: For though the cuppe of the lorde be witholden from
<pb facs="tcp:177901:23"/> the laye people for certeyne cauſes which be but trifles / yet now for aſmuch as it is euydent (to all ſuch as will know it) that the memoriall of Chriſtes holy ſupper was inſtitute by himſelfe vnder both the fourmes of bred and wyne / let vs forſake oure ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fooliſhe intentes / and turne agayne to the infallyble ordynaunce of Chriſt? yea let vs aknowlege / that Chriſt / who is wyſer then all angels or men / dyd not fornaught or without cauſe ordeyne this reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce vnder both fourmes of bred and wyne: and that yf ther were anye daunger for the laye people to haue the vſe of the chalyce (as our aduerſaries make a bablyng ther of) he coulde haue knowne it afore well ynough: howbeit in the outward vſe of the ſacrament without faith / conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth but ſmall ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as it well hath apeared in the traytour Iudas. For as ſoone as he had receaued this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the other diſciples at the hande of Chriſt immediatly went he forth / xecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / diſpayred / &amp; hanged him ſelfe. For yf the outward vſe of the bred and wyne were neceſſary to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion / it ſhuld not go well with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that
<pb facs="tcp:177901:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> maye not awaye with wyne. Therfore the right and wholſome remembraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the ſupper of the lorde / is it that is done in faith: namely / wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we beleue that the body of Chriſt was geuen for vs and that his bloude was ſhed for vs But for aſmuch as Chriſt wolde haue the ſame remembraunce kepte with outward vſyng of bred an wyne / there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore muſt ſo greate a ſacrament in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beleſt vnmyniſtred / but ſtill obſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued / acording as Chriſt himſelfe hath ordyned it / wothout all mens inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But now will we ſpeake of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</p>
            <p>The opynion of Purgatory / I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe / is taken out of the bokes &amp; wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the Heythen / for aſmuch as in the holy ſcripture of the olde &amp; new Teſtament we haue no maner of recor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for the confirmacion of anye ſuch thing. Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue taught much and euidently of the eter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall ſaluacion of the faithfull / and dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion of the vnfaithfull: but nothing of purgatory. Wherfore I thinke it not nedefull to invoke ſore agaynſt it / conſiderynge it is a thing that hath no ground / and muſt nedes fayl of it ſelfe. Oure aduerſary neuertheles had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne
<pb facs="tcp:177901:24"/> argumentes / but ſo feble / and ſo wyde from the purpoſe / that I am all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſſ aſhamed to repete them. We rerde in the boke of the Machabeus ſent to Ieruſalem twelue thouſande peces of ſyluer / to offre for the ſynnes of the deed / becauſe he had a good and deuou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te mynde concernyng the reſurrection. Now I praye the what doth that to purgatory? Who ſaieth / that it is not a good and deuoute thing to remembre the reſurrection? And wher as the Authour of the boke addeth theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: therfore is it an holy and wholſo-ſome cogitacion to praye for the deed / that they might be delyuered from ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes: the ſame wordes do not I ſo eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / that they ought to be taken for a certeyne / for aſmuch as the authour of the ſame boke is vnknowne / and the boke it ſelfe not approuide with any te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of holy ſcripture.</p>
            <p>Furthermore / in the goſpell / where as Chriſt counſeyleth vs to agree with oure aduerſary whyle we are in the waye with him / afore we come to the iudge / left the iudge delyuer us to the officer / and the officer caſt vs in preſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thou ſhalt not come forth (ſaieth Chriſt) till thou haſt prayed the vtte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſt
<pb facs="tcp:177901:24"/> farthing. With theſe wordes will Chriſt declare / that a gentle agrement is profitable / though it be done with ſome loſſe. For yf we will not agree with our aduerſary by the waye / but feare a litle loſſe / it is to be feared / that the iudge will caſt vs in perſon / and put vs to ſharper payment yea and more intollerable / then perauenture the other was / wherwith oure aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry wolde haue bene ſatiſfied. But the perſon doth oure aduerſary call here purgatory / and that which is ſpoken co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the buſyneſſes of this world doth he take vpon him to wreſt vnto the world to come / as though a man might feyne out of the wordes of Chriſt what he liſt.</p>
            <p>In like mane ralledgeth he the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonye of. S. Paul. i. Corintr. iij. Wher he ſaieth / that the fyre ſhal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue euery mans worke what it is. And yf anye mans worke burne / he ſhall ſuffre loſſe: but he himſelfe ſhal be ſaued / neuertheles as thorow the fyre. Here expoundeth he fyre to be purgatory / where as. S. Paul by a ſymilitude doth ſaie / that our workes ſhalbe tried like as gold / ſyluer / and other metall is tried in the fyre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:25"/>
            <p>But who can ſuffre ſuch iuglyng? Let him ſhew vs the leeſt lettre in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture / that playnlie proueth purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Yf we muſt pourge our ſynnes tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row purgatory / I praye the then for what inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dyed Chriſt? Wherfore ſhed he is bloud? Yf god be with vs / who will be agaynſt vs? Who ſpared not his ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne onely ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / but gaue him for vs all / &amp; how ſhulde he not geue vs all thinges with him: Who will accuſe the electe of god? It is god that maketh them righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous / who will condemne them: Now ſewe that the faithfull are made aigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous / and ſhal not be condemned. And who is ſo vngodly as to thinke / that the righteous god doth after this world puniſhe one vncondemned.</p>
            <p>Let this litle / but trew / be ſufficent / to ouerthrow the vayne inuencion of purgatory. And what nede was it / with this weake feare of payne / to witdrawe ſymple people from the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue of Chriſt / who neuertheles in this world hath promiſed trouble euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his faithfull / to make them fele ſom what of the puniſhment of mouch ſynne: but after death an whole / frey parfite ioye and ſaluacion / which we vndowtedly loke for in the bleſſed ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe
<pb facs="tcp:177901:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue thruſt vs downe / and therfore fey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned they this horrible bogg of purgato<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry: to the intent that we diſpayring in the aſſured and infinite mercie of god which cometh thorow Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte / mighte renne to their churches (yea to their chiſtes) to be fre from our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with vnreaſonable money / whoſe iudginent tarieth not behinde. Let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man therfore be moued by thoſe diſceat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſpretes / which (as they ſaye) do ape<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are vnto men and deſire their helpe / prayeng / that maſſes / pilgremages &amp; other like ſuperſticious ceremonies ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ye be done for them / for euen the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me night bogges / like as they in old ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me were among the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſo are they now alſo among the turkes. Nether is it wonder yf the deuel ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſguyſe him in the fourme of a dead man / ſeyng he can tranſfigure himſelfe in to an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of light. But to the intent that the vnprofitable purgatory do vs no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in oure heades / we wil go forth far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The inuocacion of ſayntes hath euen ſuch a foundacion as purgatory hath / namely none at all. But a wonderfull thing is it to expreſſe / how the ymagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue euer bene enclyned
<pb facs="tcp:177901:26"/> to ydolatrie: and therfore is it not for nought that the firſt precepte among ten / was ſo well beaten in to the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes / that they ſhulde honoure but one god / and haue no ſtraunge goddes. Now to haue a ſtraunge god / what is it els / ſaue to put hope and truſt in a creature / and not in god the maker one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? Chriſt ſaieth: come to me all ye that laboure and are ouercharged / &amp; I will refreſhe you. And what ſoeuer ye aſke the father in my name / he wil geue it you. Is that trew? I ſuppoſe no man will denye it. Yf it be trew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / why do not we beleue it? Wherfore call we not vpon god the father / thorow his onely be gotten ſone Ieſus Chriſt / ſeyng we are ſure that he denieth vs no petycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But we will ſe the argumentes of ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aduerſarye / wherbye he goeth obou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to proue the inuocation of ſaynctes. We beleue (ſaieth he) the promes of Chriſt: but becauſe we truſt not to oure owne ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth / therfore ſeke we aduoca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to pray vnto god for vs: like as it is in great prynces courtes / where mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are diſpatched by the counſelours who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prince loueth. O what a groſſe likeneſſe is that? hath a prynce mortall anye thing in this poynt that maye be
<pb facs="tcp:177901:26"/> reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled vnto god? Two ſpeciall cauſes ther be / wherfore one muſt haue to do with lordes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n erth thorow media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours &amp; aduocates / namely ignoraunce of the lordes / &amp; mutabilite of their myn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des. For they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not know what one de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyreth / excepte ſome body tell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It is alſo vncertayne / whether they will graunt that one deſyreth of them or no. But ſo is it not with god. Chriſt ſaieth your father knoweth wher of ye haue nede / afore ye praye vnto him. And what ſo euer ye praye vnto the father in my name / he will geue it you. Here is it euyde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / that nether ignoraunce ner chaunheableneſſe of mynde hath place with god. This ſymilitude alſo concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng the great prynces of the world / is falſe / like as it is falſe that they ſaye they beleue the promes of Chriſt. For yf they conſtauntly beleued that they ſhuld be heard thorow Chriſt / they wold ſeke no help of other. But ſeyng they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that they truſt not their ow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne erroure / in that they vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not / that this promes was made not tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row our deſeruyng / but thorow the deſeruyng of Chriſt. And where they will kepe them ſelues from beyng to bold of god / they fall to their owne
<pb facs="tcp:177901:27"/> hurt in to the head ſynne of deſperacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or infidelite. And yf they contynue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin / they nede not loke to opteyne any thing of god / as. S. Iames teſtifieth / who exhorteth vs to praye in faith / and not to dowte. For who ſo dowteth (ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth he) is like vnto the wawes of the ſee / that are toſſed and blowne of the wynd. Let not ſuch a man thinke / that he ſhal receaue any thing of the lorde.</p>
            <p>In matters of the world / it is not ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compted no god witt for a man to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a thing certayne for a thing vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne / and as the dogg dyd in Eſopes fables / to let the fleſh fall / and to folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the ſhadow ther of. And how much more vndiſcrete a thing maye it be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med / whan in ſuch a greate matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng euerlaſting ſaluacion / one for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaketh it that without contradiction is true / &amp; foloweth another thing / wher it maye be dowted whether it be true or no. That we are heard thorow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte / we be certayne / whyle we are ſo taught of the verite it ſelfe. But how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we be ſure that oure prayer is heard for any ſayntes ſake / ſeyng that of the inuocacion of ſaynctes there is no men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion made in the ſcripture / but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is euydentlie declared in many
<pb facs="tcp:177901:27"/> places. Chriſt anſwereth the deuell af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner: thou ſhalt worſhippe the lorde thy god / and him onely ſhalt thou honoure. And what nede we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny probacions? Let him ſhew vs one place in the ſcripture / where one ſaynt called vpon another. Yf the inuocacion of ſayntes were profitable / why dyd not Moſes call vpon Abraham Iſaac &amp; Iacob / ſeyng he heard god him ſelfe ſaye. I am the god of Abraham / Iſaac and of Iacob? Why dyd not Dauid and the other prophetes call vpon Moſes / as the chefe prophet of god? And wher / fore dyd not the Iewes that came after call vpon Dauid / who had ſuch good re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde of god himſelfe / that he ſayed / I haue found a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after myne owne hert / which ſhal accompliſhe all my will.</p>
            <p>And after the commyng of Chriſt why dyd not the Apoſtles call vpon Ihon the baptiſt / concernyng whom they had heard theſe wordes of oure Sauioure: among ſuch as are borne of women aro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe none greater then Ihon the baptiſt.</p>
            <p>It is not lickelye ye deare Iudges / that theſe holy men of whom I now haue made mencion / were ſo neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / or ſo vnkynde of ſtomake toward vs / that yf they had knowne and bene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded
<pb facs="tcp:177901:28"/> that the inuocacion of ſayntes were for oure ſaluacion or acceptable to god / they wolde not let vs knowe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. Therfore do I eſteme it a daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing / without ſcripture yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the open ſcripture / to ſet vp the inuocation of ſayntes / as a ſeruyce ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to god. Nether can I alowe the obiection of thoſe / that go aboute to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne ſuch opynions by olde and long cuſtome / or by miracles. For as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching cuſtome / yf all were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended that hath bene long and of old tyme vſed / then the blaſphemous vſe of the heithen with their ydols muſt be ſet vp agayne / which with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of ſo many nacions endured many yeares afore the commyng of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus mighte advowtrie al ſo and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vyces be manteyned / ſeyng they be committed ſo oft and in ſo many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But what is leſſe commendable / than to go aboute thorow an euell cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to ſet vp / a thing that is openly agaynſt the lawe of god / yea men in their lawes will ſuffre no ſuch euell cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms we to take vpon vs to be iudges ouer gods worde</p>
            <p>Concernyng miracles which god ſo greatly worketh in his ſayntes / who
<pb facs="tcp:177901:28"/> wolde not higlye wonder at ſuch / as at a ſyngular gift of god? Not withſton<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding it is manifeſt alſo / that to do mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles add wonders / is not allwaye a ſure probacion of holyneſſe / ſeyng we reade not euer that Abraham / Iſaac / Iacob / Dauid and Ihon the baptiſt dyd miracles. Muſt they therfore not be holy / and ſhuld we therfore deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe them? Or why call we not Iudas the traytour / as a ſaynt / that dyd mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles with the Apoſtles and healed many people / as we maye perceaue out of the hiſtorie of the goſpell? But let vs heare the ſentence of Chriſt: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (ſaieth he) ſhal ſaye vnto me in that daye: lorde / lorde / haue not we profeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thy name? Haue not we caſt out deuels in thy name? Haue we not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne great vertues in thy name? Then wil I confeſſe vnto them / I neuer kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we you. Departe frome all ye euel doers. What can oure aduerſarys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt now of ſayntes miracles / ſeyng we reade that vngodly and damned perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue done many great actes in the name of Chriſt? And. S. Paul alſo prophecieth to the Theſſalonians / ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng that the wiked ſhal come / namely the childe of perdicion / whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng
<pb facs="tcp:177901:29"/> is after the workyng of the deuell / with all maner lyeng powers / tokens and wonders. Wherfore let vs not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue euery ſprete / but proue them whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they be of god / or no. And let vs not be ſo vnaduyſed as to aſcrybe vnto ſayntes and to their merites / the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure that onely apperteyneth vnto god.</p>
            <p>Whan Peter and Ihon at the gate of the temple / had made the lame man whole / and the people ranne to them wonderyng / Peter ſayd vnto them: ye men of Iſrael / why wonder ye at this thing / or why loke ye ſo vpon vs / as though we thorow oure power or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue had made this man go. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it foloweth: throw the faith in his name (namely Chriſtes) hath he vpon this man whom ye ſe and know / confirmed his name. And faith thorow him hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> healt before you<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re eyes. Where are now the miracles which they ſaye are done thorow the merites of ſayntes? Peter and Ihon pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorus of the church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe playnlie / that this lame man was not made whole thorow their power or vertue / but in the faith thorow Chriſt. O eternall god / in what an horrible depe pitt of
<pb facs="tcp:177901:29"/> Idolatrie are we fallen? How farre ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue we erred from the true faith of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte? We ſhal not lightly fynd any tyme wher in the heithe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue honoured their goddes with ſo greate ſuperſticiouſneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe / as ſome Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honoure their ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Euery occupacion hath his advow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie / euery la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de their owne defendoure / and euery ſickneſſe a peculiar phiſician. There be ſome ſayntes alſo whom they do not honoure to haue profit by them but becauſe they ſhulde do them no har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. To certayne peculiar ſayntes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te they their matters of warre / their marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe / &amp; their cauſes of mariage. The huſband men alſo haue their owne helpers: one increaceth the ſede / ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kepeth the vynyardes / the ſhepe / the kyne / the geyſe: yea the filthye ſwy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne haue likewiſe their owne propre her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. To him offre the fooliſhe people all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maner of thinges / but for the moſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te waxe ſo that here in they are allmoſt become like vnto the Egiptians / who worſhipped ſuch beſtes themſelues for their goddes.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſayntes now are all honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / they are all called vpon: onely mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull Chriſt is not regarded. And though they ſomtyme name him with
<pb facs="tcp:177901:30"/> bare wordes / yet is all their truſt in the ſayntes. Nether are they ſatiſfied in ſuch ſtraunge honouryng of ſayntes / but make alſo a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull difference of holy places. Here of cometh it that they thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke Mary the mother of Chriſt to be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re gracious in one place / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in another. Now pilgremages alſo myniſhe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the reputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the olde. They ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to Compoſtell in Spayne to viſite. S. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: to Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in douchland to ſalute oure lady / and in many othrr places to ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes graues (as the kytes flie to the cario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) &amp; honoure many deed bodies vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth whoſe ſoules are in hell. I paſſe ouer the fooliſhe ſuperſticion that they vſe with deed ſaynctes rayment / as cotes hoſen ſhues / &amp; regarde litle the poore ſayntes / that lyue with vs as brethren in Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erth / &amp; haue greate nede of ſuch ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell. Yet wold I eſteme it a leſſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour / yf they worſhipped not alſo the ymages that haue no vnderſtondyng &amp; are made with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s handes / of gold / ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer / ſtone &amp; wodde: yea very litle it fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that they worſhippe not with al / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wormes the wormes that gnaw the bodies of ſuch bleſſed ſaynctes of wodd. To ſuch ymages aſcrybe they wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dere &amp; miracles. Of ſome one they ſaye / that it had ſpoken. Of another they ſay / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:30"/> that by his owne vertue he is gone from one place to another. They daye ſhulde be to long for me / yf I wolde ſaye all that might be ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this vnreaſonable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma they leaue nothing be hynde that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to full ydolatry</p>
            <p>We maye well ſaye / that the Indianes had much more right to worſhipe the. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / ſuch a deare / profitable / wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull &amp; excellent creature / then theſe mad folkes haue to worſhippe ſuch a rotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worme ate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ydoll. Now though we diſalowe ſuch ydo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atrie / ſuch peruerſe honouryng &amp; wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; inuocacion of ſayntes / let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke / that we therfore wil withdrawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ye thing of their true worſhipe &amp; reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sayntes haue nothing that they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not receaued Paul ſaieth: what is Paul? What is Apollo? Euen miniſtres they are / by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are to the beleue / and that accordyng as the lorde hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And afterward it foloweth: therfore let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reioyce in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / for all is yours / whether it be Paul or Apollo or Cephas or the world: whether it be life or death / whether it be thinges preſent or for to come: all is yours but ye are Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes / and Chriſt is gods. Wherfore all grace which commeth thorow Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the holy gooſt / aſcrybe we vnto god as vnto him that onely geueth it.
<pb facs="tcp:177901:31"/> And hartely we beſeke him that vnto vs poore ſynners alſo he will grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this infynite mercye / to the intent that we maye forſake oure ſynnes / and be holy before him thorow Ieſus Chriſt his onely begotten ſone / who vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe hath delyuered vs not with a ſmall pryce / but with his owne bloude. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it is / that ſayntes haue their due ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure / but faith and inuocacion belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get onely vnto god. Let us go therfore with confidence vnto the ſeate of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / that we maye receaue mercy &amp; fynde grace to helpe in the tyme of nede. For we haue not an hye preſt which can not haue compaſſidn on oure infirmities / but was in all poyntes tempted as we are but without ſynne / beyng euer able alſo to ſaue them that come vnto god thorow him / and lyueth euer to make interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for vs. Nether is ther vnder heauen geuen vnto men anye other name / wherin we muſt be ſaued. For ther is but one god / and one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatoure be twene god and man / name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the man Ieſus Chriſt / which gaue himſelfe a redempcion for all. To him be honour and praiſe for euer.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe was (Right deare Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges) to haue defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded this Chriſten man
<pb facs="tcp:177901:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> cauſe with few wordes. Neuertheles the ſotyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playnt of our aduerſary hath hyndred me (as ye ſe) fro makyng of myne anſwere. Wherfore the faulte of ſo lang communicacion ought reaſona<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly to be imputed not vnto vs / but to the vnrighteous accuſer.</p>
            <p>And now wyll I take in hand the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xte article / namely auricular co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion: which I ſuppoſe was firſt ordyned for this purpoſe / that the ſymple vnlerned people ſhulde go to the preſtes to ſeke counſaill / yf they had anye greuous thing in their mynde either cocernyng eny dowte in the beleue / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng ſynne which vexeth a mans conſcience: To the intent that the preſtes as they that be lerned and haue experience in the ſcripture / might ſtrenght ſuch as be weake in faith / warne the vnrulye and miſnurtoured / comforte ſuch as be ſory and penitent for their ſynnes: ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma / as true phiſicians to geue due me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycines for euery ſickneſſe. Which or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce yf it were right kepte / and as I now haue ſayde / I ſuppoſe no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could reproue it. But now foraſmuch as they commaunde / that euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ones in the yare confeſſe all his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to his owne preſt not onely ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:177901:32"/> as he hath committed in dede / but alſo what ſoeuer is come in to his thought / yea and to declare the ſtate / place / ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and circumſtaunce of the perſones / conſidering likewiſe that they procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the ſame out as a commaundment of god vnder payne of eternall damma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / I maye ſaye that it is no wholſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me confeſſion of ſynnes / but rather a ſhamelfull tormenting of mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences. Nether can I beleue ether / but that it was brought in by the ſpeciall craft and ſotiltie of the deuel / to tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle poore men with a new ſnare / and vttarlye to bring them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wholſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me and neceſſary confeſſion of ſynnes. It is written in the pſalme: I ſayde / I wil euen agaynſt my ſelfe / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne offence vnto the lorde / and thou for gaueſt me the vngodlyneſſe of my ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne. For the ſame ſhal all ſaynctes praye vnto the in due ſeaſon. Without ſuch confeſſion of ſynne ſhal noman be ſaued. For they that deſyre to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the grace of Chriſt / muſt afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re al thinges know and confeſſe / that they are ſynners and worthy of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall puniſhment. Such a confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf it come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hert / is wholſome &amp; frute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Afterward verely foloweth a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hert / which god will not diſpiſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:32"/>
            <p>Oure aduerſary wolde proue out of the goſpell / that this confeſſion to the preſt / is commaunded of Chriſt / becau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that whan he clenſed the lepars / he bad them go ſhew them ſelues to the preſtes. Here doth oure aduerſary ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a colde interpretacion. Shew youre ſelues / ſaieth he / is aſmuch to ſaye / as confeſſe youre ſynnes. But the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that folowe after in the goſpell / wil not ſuffre ſuch a ſlender expoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And offre the gift (ſaieth Chriſt) that Moſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded / for a witneſſe vnto them. This was the very cauſe why they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to go vnto the preſtes: namely / that of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / as of thoſe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the knowlege of leproſie was committed / they might be iudged clea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne: to the intent it might be knowne / that Chriſt had truly clenſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther frre for a witneſſe agaynſt ſuch as reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted him / bad he the lepers offre the gift that Moſes had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the lawe.</p>
            <p>Out of. S. Iames epiſtle taketh our aduerſary theſe wordes: knowlege your ſynnes one to another / and praye one for another / that ye maye be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Here doth he as he dyd afore / and will haue this worde one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her / to be aſmuch to ſaye as to a preſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:33"/>
            <p>Neuertheles the wordes be ſo playne / that they nede no long interpretacion. For. S. Iames willeth / that euery one ſhal knowlege himſelf as a ſynner to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his neggboure / &amp; ſo one to praye for another / that they maye fulfill bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therley loue and be ſaued. I abhorre (moſt prudent Iudges) to expreſſe / what greate harme the ſtraite confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath brought to paſſe among the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people. For ſeyng they thinke that they can not be ſaued / exerpte they con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe euery thing as narowly as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſhriſt tradicion byndeth / and yet lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it vndone ſomtyme for ſhame / and ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme thorow forgetfulneſſe / no doute they fall in to deſpayre / and are euer (yea aſlong as they lyue) farre from ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly hope. It is manifeſt alſo how vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably certayne preſtes behaue them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues in hearing of confeſſions / to the greate deſtruction of ſoules. Some / for all yght occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / will not abſolue a peni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent / no though he be very ſory for his ſynnes. Some aſke queſtions of yong people concernyng wanton and filthie mattters / nothing regarding their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent myndes. And where as they ſhulde erneſtly deſyre to helpe with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me wholſowe medycine / they make
<pb facs="tcp:177901:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> deedly woundes in weake conſciences.</p>
            <p>But what ſhal I ſaye? Haue they not oft and wilfully thorow their conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / abuſed the chaiſt ſymplicite of honeſt weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and virgyns / to their owne vnchaſtite and wantonneſſe? So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of them openly tolde abrode / the thing that hath bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to their fidelite in confeſſion: and therby haue they brought much malyce to paſſe / yea and ſomtyme murthur alſo. Such are the ſwete frutes of this fayned con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion: yea and that as euell is / they preach the ſame to be a worke / for who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſake god forgeueth ſynnes and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by haue they robbed Chriſt of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure / like blaſphemous men as they be. Wherfore conſidering this tre was not planted by the father of heauen / but by the children of the deuel / to ſearch out craftely the priuyties of mens hertes / me thinketh it ſhulde be pluckte vp by the rootes / and men brought agayne to the right and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome confeſſion of their ſynnes.</p>
            <p>The reſt is / that I make anſwere touching the difference of meates / and concernyng the mariage of preſtes: Which two poyntes I purpoſe not to ſonder / far aſmuch as Paul ioyneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:177901:34"/> together in his firſt epiſtle to Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy / where theſe be his wordes: the ſpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſpeaheth euidently / that in the later tymes ſome ſhal departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith / and ſhal geue hede vnto ſpretes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and deueliſhe doctrynes of them which ſpeake falſe thorow ypocriſie &amp; haue their conſcience marked with an hote yron / forbydding to mary / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding to obſteyne from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes which god hath created to be recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with thankeſgeuyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which beleue and know the trueth. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature of god is good / &amp; nothing to be refuſed / that is receaued with ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of thankes: for it is ſanctified by the word of god and praier (I ſuppoſe deare iudges) that as touching theſe matters / Paul hath with theſe wordes ſufficienthly anſwered for vs / ſeyng he ſaieth euidently / that they which for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byd to mary / and commaunde to abſtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne fro meates / are departed from the faith and folow the deuels doctryne.</p>
            <p>Paul alſo him ſelf wrythet thus to the Corinthians: what ſo euer is ſolde in the fleſh market / that eate / and aſke no queſtion for conſcience ſake. For the erth is the lordes / and all that is the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin. And to the Coloſſians he wryteth:
<pb facs="tcp:177901:34"/> let no man therfore trouble youre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences aboute meat or drynke / or for a pece of an holy daye / or new Moone / or of the Saboath daies / which are the ſhadow of thinges that were for to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / but the body it ſelfe is in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And afterward it foloweth: yf ye be deed then with Chriſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the world why are ye holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſuch tradicions / as thoug ye liued after the world? As whan they ſaye / Touche not this / taiſt not that / ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dle not that: All which thisges do hurte vnto men becauſe of their obuſe / which commeth onely of the commaundmentes and doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trynes of men. etc. All this doth Chriſt confirme / whan he ſaieth: what ſoeuer entreth in at the mouth / defyleth not the man. And what can be more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? But ſo falſe and vnrighteous is the iudgment of ſuch vnreaſonable me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that yf a Chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do taiſt but a litle fleſh vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a daye prohibited by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Immediatly without any farther advi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſement / they proclame him to be an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike / and caſt in his tethe ſuch a tradi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of faſting / as though a mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion depended vpon the difference of meates: and yet the ypocrites them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / though they eate no fleſhe / are ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertheleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:177901:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo full of fleſllye deſyres / that they can vnderſtond nothing but fleſhlye / &amp; ſomtyme are not aſhamed to vtter their fleſhely luſtes with exceſſe.</p>
            <p>Euen as greate wrong do they tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row their damnynge of preſtes maria<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. But to the intent that men ſhulde iudge them to be excellent manteyners of chaſtite / they prayſe virginite out of meaſure / which in very dede is a ſingu gift of god / but keuen vnto few. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe that they go aboute to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / not virginite / but a ſtate to liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried / it appeareth playnlie by this / that whan a preſt taketh a wife / they wil not onely haue him depoſed from his myniſtracion / but iudge him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be put to death alſo. But yf he agaynſt all honeſtie / take an harlot / or kepe another mans wife / he is ſuffred / as a profitable membre of the church (of Rome I meane). O what an horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wickendeſſe is this? Yet was ther neuer a people ſo wilde or vnnaturall / but they had an ordynaunce concernyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge mariage / and keping of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cubynes. Onely Romiſhe preſtes maye in this matter do as they luſt themſelues.</p>
            <p>They take harlottes at their pleaſure / whan they will / and where / and aſke
<pb facs="tcp:177901:35"/> no queſtion for conſcience ſake / ſo that they paye the biſhope the whore toll.</p>
            <p>And euen with like audacyte put they them awaye from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agayne / and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me neuer a whitt. Yet are they not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied with ſuch vnmeaſurable liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie / but haunt other mens wifes / and defloure virgynite. No thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſafe from them: with their filthie wantoneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe defyle they euery thing / the angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call defenders of chaſtite: all which is ſo manifeſt / that it can not be hydd.</p>
            <p>But leſt I be reputed more to be an accuſer of Romiſhe preſtes / then a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of this Chriſten man / I will paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ouer many thinges that might be ſpoken concernyng this matter / and conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me with the iudgment of Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ul / who ſaieth: yf they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not abſteyne / let them mary / for it is better eo mary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to burne. Wherfore let this iudgment remayne / let troubled co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences be hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped / and the myniſtres of the church reſtored agayne to an honeſt conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: leſt yf we contynue in this ſynne / we fall in to that horrible iudgment / wherwith god will iudge fornicatours and aduoutres.</p>
            <p>Now / thou vnreaſonable accuſer / haſt thou a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t anſwere to all the poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:177901:36"/> of thy complaynte? and I wold ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe that thy madneſſe ſhulde therbye be mitigate / yf I feared not that the light of thy body were darkened for very ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyce. Now yf the light that is in the be darkneſſe / how grerte wil the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe be / euen thou thy ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe / I ſaye knoweſt well / that all that I haue ſayde / is true. And why reſiſted thou than the open trueth. Thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy man / art thou ſo farre vnaduy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed / that thou canſt not po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre / how wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a groud thou haſt in this vngodly matter / and agayne how mightie and invyncyble an aduerſary thou haſt / na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely Chriſt Ieſus the onely begotten deare ſone of god. Thy furye hath now raged ynough agaynſt this innocent Chriſten man, Ceaſſe now at the laſt from peruerting the right waye of the lorde. Alas man / how oft haſt thou in this thy enuyous complaynte / denyed the faith openly / in that thou haſt dyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe tymes ſayde / that onely faith maketh not righteous before god? I praye the / art thou not aſhamed of ſo deteſtable a lye? Doth not the ſcripture teach eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently / that fait onely iuſtifieth in the fight of god: Who euer denyed this / yf he were not mad / and ſuch one as thou
<pb facs="tcp:177901:36"/> art? Thou boſteſt of great workes / wher of thou thy ſelfe haſt not touched one with thy litle fyngre. And who knoweth not / that faith and charite can not be ſeparated. Yf charite then hang vpon faith / and can not be yd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le / but allwaye occupied / how ſhul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de not the workes of charite and loue folow afterwarde of theim ſelues? Yea the ſame workes are now not oures (leſt any man boaſt himſelfe) but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes / who worketh in vs thorow faith / as in his owne membres.</p>
            <p>Thou takeſt to recorde the Epiſtle of. S. Iames / whoſe wordes are theſe: faith without workes is deed. Here thou reioyceſt as though thou haddeſt gotten the vittory / and tryumpheſt as though thou wereſt ouer the hedge all ready. S. Iames ſaieth / that faith wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout workes is no faith / for faith lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue or charite ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſondred. Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thow that one can loue another / to whom he geueth no credence Or that one ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put all his hope and truſt in him whom he loueth not S. Paul ſaieth: yf I had all faith / ſo that I coulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue hilles / and hadde not loue / I we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re nothing. The ſame putteth he for a thing vnpoſſible / and declareth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bye
<pb facs="tcp:177901:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
/ that faith can not be without loue or charite. Therfore will we diſcerne theſe thre thinges (faith hope and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite) one from another / but ſo / that they remayne vnſeparated. Faith onely iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth before god: loue or charite wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth toward hir neghboure: hope doth pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly wayte for the promes of god / and ſhal not be confounded. Thou ſaieſt we lacke good workes / (not ſuch as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of loue / or that Chriſt ſhal requyre of vs at the daye of iudgment) but to go a pilgremage / to ſet vp ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dils befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ymages / to nombre vp what we pray / to tell ouer a payre of beedes / to put deffence in clothing / in meates / in prayers / in titels or names / wher one had rather be called a charter houſe monck or a barfote frere / then a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man. Theſe and ſuch like ſklender and childiſhe workes requyreſt thou of vs: which though one had done them alltogether / it were euen aſmuch as though he in the meane ſeaſon had ryd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den vpon a ſticke with boyes in the ſtrete.</p>
            <p>But declare thou vs thy faith out of ſuch workes / as belong to a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man / and we wil ſhew the oure workes put of faith. Seiſt thou how this Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:177901:37"/> mam (whom thou accuſeſt) ſtondeth he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſo weake &amp; fleble thorow the ſtynck and tedyouſneſſe of the preſon / that he can ſcace ſtond vpon his legges. And why: I praye the. Hath he committed anye euell dede? No. For yf he haue done ouhht that deſerueth death / or ſo the Iudges haue the law / they haue the ſwerde / let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> execute it / I wil ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke no requeſt agaynſt it. Wherfore is it than? I wil tell the. Euen becauſe he hath frely preached the goſpell of Chriſt and the grace that is geuen vs thorow him (for he beleued / therfore hath he ſpoken) and hath taught that what ſoeuer is agaynſt the goſpell ought to be put dawne / to the intent that the kyngdome of god might come vnto vs / &amp; that his name might be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified: thus of a feruent loue hath he endeuored himſelfe to inſtructe all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to bring them to the true knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of god / and of his ſone Ieſus Chriſt Summa / his mynde was ſo ſet to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his negboure / that he hath not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred the darck dongeon and preſon / to be deſolate and alone / in honger and thirſt / yea &amp; in daunger of death.</p>
            <p>Such are the workes of a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which muſt not be aſcrybed vnto vs / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:38"/> but vnto the lorde that worketh them in vs. Such true faſting is accepted of the lorde ſuch true obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce belongeth to his ſayntes.</p>
            <p>Now foraſmuch as I haue ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ently declared that oure aduerſaries complaynte is cleane agaynſt equyte / ther is no more to be requyred ſaue onely that ye / Right deare Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (whoſe mynde is to do euery man right) quyte this Chriſten man acording to you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177901:38"/>
            <head>A ſhort recapittulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Reader.</head>
            <p>Here haſte thou harde (moſte Ie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le Reader) how beninge / how lovinge / how myndfull owre moſte mercifull father is / and ever hat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the ben / ouer his electe and choſyn chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren / namely eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now. And for an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample haue we this poore and ſimple creture ſett before owre iees / to calle vs to remembrance that he is ny vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all them that / in tyme of tribulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſecucion will calle / a pon hym in treweth and verite. Se we not here how mercifully. He ſtirechith owte his hande / he ſpredith a broude his wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to hyde and cover this his tender birde frome the gleyde or boſarde. And in concluſion he mollifieth and movith the harte of this verteouſe prince and by hym as by an enſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his one / doeth he not only defende this poore mans cauſe / or rather the trewthyt ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe: but alſo delyueryth him frome the cruell ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of all his emnies / no other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe / the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evin as it were frome death to lyfe ſoche is his godly nature / ſoche is his properte an a cuſtomed maner / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:39"/> that in the mydiſt of aduerſytes tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion &amp; perſecucion / where men thinck him moſte furthiſt of / ther is he moſte nyeſt and preſent / with ſoche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolacion and comforth as canne not be expreſſid wyth / tonge. What more Ioye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ther come to them whiche be afflicted perſecuted and vnder the ſwete croſſe of Ieſu Chriſt / then to calle to ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance the confortable ſtoryes of the ſcripture acording to the ſayeng of ſent Paul. What ſo euer thyng is wrytten / it is wrytton for owre doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne and lernyng / that throwgh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience and the conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of godes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / we may haue ſewre hope &amp; truſte.</p>
            <p>Hou lycke a loving lorde / ſaued he / Iſaac / frome the mortall and deadly ſtrock of the ſwerde / with howe petiful aneye lokyd he on Noe the precher of ryghteouſneſſe / reſtoryng hym frome the rough ragyng wawes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull ſee / he deliuerid Loth at an enſtant frome the conuerſacion and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of they vngodly Sodomytes &amp; Gomorrians / keppt he not Ionas ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and ſownde / after he was devoured and ſwaloed vp of that houge and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruus fiſhe: Sydrach / Miſach / and Ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denago / preſerued he frome the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng
<pb facs="tcp:177901:39"/> fornace of burnyng fyrd Daniel be deliueryd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the devouryng mow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes / of the hongry lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Moiſes amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the reedes and flages hydde &amp; hangyd by the water ſyde in a baſkyd / whas re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtored agayne to his naturall mother to be norſed of her. Paul was left dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in a baſkyt / and ſo eſcaped the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of his perſecuters / Suſanna / whas preſerued and defended pure and vnde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filed / frome the lecherus luſtes of the falſe preſtes and Iudges / Iudith / with moche Ioye and victorye whas dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueryd frome the feyrce violence / and myghty power of all they emnies of god. Theſe / and many mo godly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples be lefftt in the holy ſcripture to the great comforth and conſolation of them that ſuffer perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſake / acording to the ſaieng of Chriſt hym ſelfe. Bleſſed are all they which ſuffer perſecucion for ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes ſake: for theyr is the kyngdome of heauen. Agayne / as many as will lyue godly in Chriſte Ieſu muſte ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution / it is the bleſſyng of god &amp; the ſwete rodde of correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / where wyth all the feathe of the feathfull muſt ther wyth betryed. For evyn as owre lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and god / doeth all wayes and at all tymes
<pb facs="tcp:177901:40"/> preſerue / kepe / and defende his poore perſecuted &amp; afflicte in al extremites: ſo doeth he caſte downe / and neuer rayſe vp agayne / all ſoche that ſo obſtinatly and wilfully reſiſtyth his eternall teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment and worde / oppreſſyng his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers / and perſecutyng Chriſt / the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſone of god in his members. Seyeng now that ſoche trowble and perſecuci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on chanſith all wayes apon the ſimple and pore afflicte / ſpecially now / in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe dangerus &amp; perelus ſeyſon: let not therfore the wordes of Paul be owte of they reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be at liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / where he ſayeth Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre them that are in bandes / evyn as though ye were in bandes wich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and be myndfull off them whiche are in aduerſite: Lett this ſhorte an breſſe leſſon / be ſuffycient at this tyme to put the / (moſte Chriſten reader) in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of ſome paerte of thy dewty: and to render thanckes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the lorde for the great ſtrength and power he gaue vnto this Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to confeſſe his lord &amp; god / before all men hym ſhalle the lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne before the father of heven / the lorde ſende vs many ſoche prynces that wil wyth ſo redy a mynd defende the lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worde of god / deliuer the innocent / 
<pb facs="tcp:177901:40"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fute the falſe accuſer / and to conclude to be preſt &amp; redy to gyue his lyffe for his pore brother. To the great diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth of that hongry horſe leche / and bloude thyrſti Romanyſt the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (of wome) ys never ſatiſfied tyl yt hathe bloud. God defende all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue in hys worde frome ther cruelite / and ylluminate they hertes of all prynces that they maye oneſt ſpye and perceyue what kynde of people they be that cauſe thys great diſſenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſcorde and warres / now in this trowbelous tyme / and thou I put no dowte but that kyngdome of antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte / whyche now hangyth by a twyne threde / ſhall ſhortly take a falle / &amp; the kyngdome of Chriſte magnyfied amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge all nacyons to the great honor and lawde of god: to the conſolacion and confort of the wolle Chriſten congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſu Chriſte / to whome be prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe both now &amp; euer. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed at Nurenbergh / And tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated owt of douche in to Engliſhe by Myles Couerdale / in the yeare of our Lorde, M.D.XLV. in the laſte of Octobre.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
